Wonder by RJ palasio 1 to 10 MOM ALWAYS HAD this
habit of asking me how something felt on a scale of 1 to 10 It started after I
had my jaw surgery, when I couldn’t talk because my mouth was wired shut. They had
taken a piece of bone from my hipbone to insert into my chin to make it look more
normal, so I was hurting and a lot of different places. Mom would point to one
of my bandages, and I would hold up my fingers to show her how much it was
hurting. One meant a little bit 10 meant so, so, so much. Then she would tell the
doctor when he made his rounds what needed adjusting or things like that. Mom
got very good at reading my mind sometimes. After that, we got into the
habit of doing the 1 to 10 scale for anything that hurt, like if I just had a
plain old sore throat, she’d asked 1 to
10 And I’d say: “Three,” or whatever it was.
When school was over, I went outside to meet Mom, who was waiting for me at the
front entrance like all the other parents are baby sitters The first thing
she said after hugging me was: So how was it 1 to
10 Five,” I said, shrugging, which I could tell totally surprised her.
“Wow,” she said quietly, “that’s even better than I hoped for.” “Are we picking Via up?”
“Miranda’s mother is picking her up today.
Do you want me to carry your backpack, sweetness?” We had started walking through
the crowd of kids and parents, most of whom were noticing me, “secretly” pointing
me out to each other. “I’m fine,” I said. “It looks too heavy, Auggie.” She started to
take it from me.
“Mom!” I said, pulling my backpack away from her. I walked in front of her through the
crowd. “See you tomorrow, August!” It was Summer. She was walking in the opposite
direction. “Bye, Summer,” I said, waving at her. As soon as we crossed the street and
were away from the crowd, Mom said: “Who is that, Auggie?” “Summer.” “Is she in your class?”
“I have lots of classes.” “Is she in any of your classes?” Mom said. “Nope.” Mom waited
for me to say something else, but I just didn’t feel like talking. “So it went okay?”
said Mom. I could tell she had a million questions she wanted to ask me. “Everyone
was nice? Did you like your teachers?” “Yeah.” “How about those kids you
met last week? Were they nice?” “Fine, fine.
Jack hung out with me a lot.” “That’s so great, sweetie. What about that boy
Julian?” I thought about that dark cious comment. By now it felt like that had
happened a hundred years ago. “He was okay,” I said. “And the blonde
girl, what was her name?” “Charlotte. Mom, I said everyone was nice
already.” “Okay,” Mom answered. I honestly don’t know why I was kind of mad at Mom,
but I was. We crossed Ams for Avenue, and she didn’t say anything else until we
turned onto our block. “So,” Mom said. “How did you meet
Summer if she wasn’t in any of your classes?” “We sat together at lunch,” I said.
I had started kicking a rock between my feet like it was a soccer ball, chasing
it back and forth across the sidewalk.
“She seems very nice.” “Yeah, she is is She’s very pretty,” Mom said. “Yeah, I know,” I
answered. “We’re kind of like Beauty in the Beast.” I didn’t wait to see Mom’s
reaction. I just started running down the sidewalk after the rock, which I had
kicked as hard as I could in front of me Padawan THAT NIGHT I cut off the little
braid on the back of my head. Dad noticed first. “Oh good,” he said. “I never like like
that thing.” Via couldn’t believe I had cut it off. “That took you years to grow!”
she said, almost like she was angry. “Why did you cut it off?” “I don’t know,” I
answered. “Did someone make fun of it?” “No.” “Did you tell Christopher you were
cutting it off?” “We’re not even friends anymore!” “That’s not true,” she said. “I can’t
believe you would just cut it off like that,” she added SN
and then practically slammed my bedroom door shut as she left the room. I was
snuggling with Daisy on my bed when Dad came to tuck me in later. He scooched
Daisy over gently and laid down next to me on the blanket. “So, Auggie doggy he
said, “it was really an okay day?” He got that from an old cartoon about a docon
named Auggie doggy by the way. He had bought it for me on eBay when I was about
and we watched it a lot for a while— —especially in the hospital. He would call
me Augie Doggy and I would call him “dear old Dad,” like the puppy called the docon
dad on the show. “Yeah, it was totally okay,” I said,
nodding. “You’ve been so quiet all night
long.” “I guess I’m tired.” “It was a long day,
huh?” I nodded. “But it really was okay?” I nodded again. He didn’t say anything, so
after a few seconds, I said: “It was better than okay,
actually.” “That’s great to hear, Auggie,” he said quietly, kissing my forehead. “So it
looks like it was a good call Mom made you're going to
school.” “Yeah. But I could stop going if I wanted to, right?” “That was the deal, yes,” he
answered. “Though I guess it would depend on why you wanted to stop going, too, you
know. You’d have to let us know. You’d
have to talk to us and tell us how you’re feeling, and if anything bad was
happening. Okay? You promise you’d tell us?” “Yeah.” “So can I ask you something? Are you
mad at Mom or something? You’ve been kind of huffy with her all night long. You
know, Auggie, I’m as much to blame for
sending you to school as she is.” “No, she’s more to blame. It was her idea.” Mom
knocked on the door just then and peaked her head inside my room. “Just wanted to
say good night,” she said. She looked kind of shy for a second. “Hi Mama Dad said,
picking up my hand and waving it at her. “I heard you cut off your braid,” Mom
said to me, sitting down at the edge of
the bed next to Daisy. “It’s not a big
deal,” I answered quickly. “I didn’t say it
was,” said Mom. “Why don’t you put Auggie to bed tonight?” Dad said to Mom, getting up.
“I’ve got some work to do anyway. Good night, my son, my son.” That was another
part of our Augie Doggy routine, though I wasn’t in the mood to say Good night,
dear old Dad. “I’m so proud of you,” said
Dad, and then he got up out of the bed.
Mom and Dad had always taken turns putting me to bed. I knew it was a little
babyish of me to still need them to do
that, but that’s just how it was with us.
“Will you check in on Via?” Mom said to Dad
as she laid down next to me. He stopped by the door and turned around. “What’s
wrong with Via?” “Nothing,” said Mom, shrugging, “at least that she would tell
me. But first day of high school and all that H said Dad, and then he pointed his
finger me and wait It’s always something with you kids, isn’t it?” he said. “Never a
dll moment,” said Mom. “Never a dll moment,” Dad repeated. “Good night, guys.” As soon as
he closed the door, Mom pulled out the book she’d been reading to me for the
last couple of weeks. I was relieved because I really was afraid she’d want
to “talk,” and I just didn’t feel like doing that. But Mom didn’t seem to want
to talk, either. She just flipped through the pages until she got to where we had
left off. We were about halfway through The Hobbit Stop! stop! shouted Thoren said
Mom, reading aloud, but it was too late, the excited dwarves had wasted their
last arrows, and now the bows that Beorn had given them were useless They were a
gloomy party that night, and the gloom gathered still deeper on them in the
following days. They had crossed the enchanted stream; but beyond it the path
seemed to straggle on just as before, and in the forest they could see no
change I’m not sure why, but all of a
sudden I started to cry. Mom put the book down and wrapped her arms around me. She
didn’t seem surprised that I was crying.
“It’s okay,” she whispered in my ear. “It’ll be
okay.” “I’m sorry,” I said between sniffles sh she said, wiping my tears with the
back of her hand. “You have nothing to be sorry
about. “Why do I have to be so ugly, Mommy?”
I whispered. “No, baby, you’re not “I know I
am.” She kissed me all over my face. She kissed my eyes that came down too far.
She kissed my cheeks that looked punched in. She kissed my tortoise mouth. She said
soft words that I knew were meant to help me, but words can’t change my
face Wake Me Up When September Ends THE REST OF September was hard. I wasn’t used
to getting up so early in the morning. I wasn’t used to this whole notion of
homework. And I got my first “quiz” at the end of the month. I never got “quizzes”
when Mom homeschooled me. I also didn’t like how I had no free time anymore.
Before, I was able to play whenever I wanted to, but now it felt like I always
had stuff to do for school. And being at school was awful in the beginning. Every
new class I had was like a new chance for kids to “not stare” at me. They would
sneak peeks at me from behind their notebooks or when they thought I wasn’t
looking. They would take the longest way around me to avoid bumping into me in
any way, like I had some germ they could catch, like my face was
contagious. In the hallways, which were always crowded, my face would always
surprise some unsuspecting kid who maybe hadn’t heard about me. The kid would make
the sounds you make when you hold your breath before going underwat a little “uh!”
sound. This happened maybe four or five times a day for the first few weeks: on
the stairs, in front of the lockers, in the library 500 kids in a school:
eventually every one of them was going to see my face at some time. And I knew
after the first couple of days that word had gotten around about me, because every
once in a while I’d catch a kid elbowing his friend as they passed me were
talking behind their hands as I walked by them. I can only imagine what they
were saying about me. Actually, I prefer not to even try to imagine it. I’m not
saying they were doing any of these things in a me way, by the way: not once
did any kid laugh or make noises or do anything like that there would just
being normal dumb kids. I know that. I kind of wanted to tell them that. Like,
it’s okay I know I’m weird looking take
a look, I don’t bite. Hey, the truth is, if
a wook started going to the school all of a sudden, I’d be curious, I’d probably
stare a bit! And if I was walking with Jack or Summer, I’d probably whisper to
them: Hey, there’s the Wookie And if the wook caught me saying that, he’d know I
wasn’t try to be mean. I was just pointing out the fact that he’s a
wook It took about one week for the kids
in my class to get used to my face. These
were the kids I’d see every day in all my
classes. It took about 2 weeks for the rest of the kids of my grade to get used
to my face the These were the kids I’d see in the cafeteria, yard time, PE, music,
library, computer class. It took about a month for the rest of the kids in the
entire school to get used to it. These were the kids in all the other grades.
They were big kids, some of them. Some of them had crazy haircuts. Some of them had
earrings in their noses. Some of them had pimples. None of them looked like
me Jack will I HUNG OUT with Jack and Home Room English, history, computer, music,
and science, which were all the classes we had together. The teachers assigned
seats in every class, and I ended up sitting next to Jack in every single
class, so I figured either the teachers were told to put me and Jack together, or
it was a totally incredible coincidence. I walked to classes with
Jack, too. I know he noticed kids staring at me, but he pretended not to notice. One
time, though, on our way to history, this huge eighth grader who was zooming down
the stairs two steps at a time accidentally bumped into us at the
bottom of the stairs and knocked me down.
As the guy helped me stand up, he got a look at my face, and without even meaning
to, he just said: “Whoa!” Then he patted me on the shoulder,
like he was tusting me off, and took off after his friends.
For some reason, me and Jack started cracking up. “That guy made the funniest
face!” said Jack as we sat down at our desk I know, right?” I said. “He was like,
whoa “I swear, I think he wet his pants!” We were laughing so hard that the teacher,
Mr roach had to ask us to settle down. Later, after we finished reading
about how ancient samarians built dials Jack whispered: “Do you ever want to beat those
kids up?” I shrugged guess. I don’t know.” “I’d want to.
I think you should get a secret squirt gun or something and attach it to your
eyes somehow. And every time someone stares at you, you would squirt them in
the face.” “With some green slime or something,” I answered. “No, no: with slug
juice mixed with dog p Yeah!” I said, completely agreeing. “Guys,” said Mr roach from across
the room. “People are still reading.” We nodded and looked down at our books. Then
Jack whispered: “Are you always going to look this way, August? I mean, can’t you
get plastic surgery or something?” I smiled and pointed to my
face. “Hello? This is after plastic surgery!” Jack clap clapped his hand over
his forehead and started laughing hysterically. “Dude, you should sue your
doctor!” he answered between giggles. This time the two of us were laughing so much
we couldn’t stop, even after Mr roach came over and made us both switch chairs
with the kids next to us MR Brown's October precept Mr Brown's PRECEPT FOR October
was: YOUR DEEDS ARE YOUR MONUMENTS He told us that this was written on the
tombstone of some Egyptian guy that died thousands of years ago. Since we were
just about to start studying ancient Egypt and history, Mr Brown thought this
was a good choice for a precept. Our homework assignment was to write a
paragraph about what we thought the precept meant or how we felt about it.
This is what I wrote: This precept means that we should be remembered for the
things we do. The things we do are the most important things of all. They are
more important than what we say or what we look like. The things we do outlast
our mortality. The things we do are like monuments that people build to honor
heroes after they’ve died. They’re like the pyramids that the Egyptians built to
honor the pharaohs. Only instead of being made out of stone, they’re made out of
the memories people have of you. That’s why your deeds are like your monuments.
Built with memories instead of with stone
[Music]